Finding Aid for Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (University of Michigan) publications, 1984-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (University of Michigan) publications 1984-2011
University of Michigan. Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center
2 linear feet
9756 Bimu 2
Program founded in 1986 to increase campus awareness of sexual assault and provide counseling and education services to sexual assault victims and the larger campus community. Printed materials include brochures, flyers, manuals, newsletters, and posters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit. NO.
Periodic additions to the publications are expected.
The publications are open without restriction.
The origins of the Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (SAPAC) lie in a January 1985 student sit-in in the office of the Vice-President for Student Services to address women's safety on campus and promote the opening of a rape crisis center. In May of that year, University of Michigan executive officers approved $75,000 for an anti-assault program. In February 1986, SAPAC opened as a division of Student Services, with Julie Steiner serving as Coordinator and the offices located in the Union. Its mission was to "provide counseling, education, information, and assistance to assault survivors, students, and the university community." Some of SAPAC's early activities included training of peer educators to lead workshops, presentations to new students and parents during Summer Orientation to increase awareness of sexual assault issues, organization of Sexual Assault Awareness Week, formation of SAFEWALK, a walking escort program, and the hiring of a counselor to provide counseling and advocacy services to sexual assault survivors. In 1988, SAPAC launched a 24-hour Crisis Line providing support and counseling to survivors. In 2008, in conjunction with SafeHouse Center in Ann Arbor and with funding from the U.S. Department of Justice's Office of Violence Against Women, SAPAC developed a nationally-recognized toolkit called "Striving for Justice: A Toolkit for Judicial Resolution Officers on College Campuses" to increase awareness of sexual assault issues among individuals working in student conflict resolution. SAPAC held a 25th anniversary concert in October 2011 and a weekend-long anniversary celebration in April 2012.
Source: Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center. "Our History." Accessed July 25, 2012. http://sapac.umich.edu/article/158.
The Publications (2.0 linear feet) consists of one series: Unit Publications.
The Unit Publications series includes brochures describing how to prevent rape in addition to brochures announcing the annual "sexism in advertising" contest. There are flyers announcing events sponsored by the Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (SAPAC) during U-M Sexual Assault Awareness Week. The bulk of this publications group consists of manuals. Noteworthy manuals include those concerning the Center's Crisis Line, and volunteer training manuals. There are also three editions of the Sexual Assault Intervention Handbook, which provides basic information for the SAPAC staff and other individuals who seek to intervene and assist in the recovery of assault victims. There is an almost complete run of the newsletter From the Center dating from 1987 to 1990.
Subjects:
U-M Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center
Genre Terms:
Manuals.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.
- Unit Publications
  - Anthologies
    - Writing to Stop Violence Against Women (Prism III), 1996 (Box 1)
  - Brochures, 1984-1999 (Box 1)
  - Coursepacks
    - Domestic Violence, undated (Box 1)
    - Sexual Assault, undated (Box 1)
    - Sexual Harassment and Stalking, undated (Box 1)
  - Flyers
    - General, 1989-1996 and undated (Box 1)
    - Myths, undated (Box 1)
    - U-M Sexual Assault Awareness Week, 1991-1995 (Box 1)
  - Invitations, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Crisis Line, 1994-2004, 9 volumes (Box 1)
    - Department of Public Safety Sexual Assault Training Manual, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Information from the University of Michigan Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center, undated (Box 1)
    - Law Enforcement Response to Sexual Assault: A Quick Reference Guide, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Networking, Publicity, and Action Reference Manual, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Peer Education
      - Program Supplement, undated (Box 1)
      - Reference Manual, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Responding to Rape: Helping Survivors Heal, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Sexual Assault Intervention Handbook, [1987], 1988 [1990] (4th edition) (Box 1)
    - Stalking: Information and Resources for your Safety, undated (Box 1)
    - Survivors of Sexual Assault Handbook, circa 2011 (Box 1)
    - Volunteer Training, 1988-2006, 17 volumes (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - Aware, 2001 (Box 2)
    - From the Center, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
    - SAPAC News, 2011 (Box 2)
    - SAPAC Newsletter, 1994 (Box 2)
    - The SAPAC Solar, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - SAPAC Speaks, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Super SAPAC Volunteers, 2002 (Box 2)
  - Posters, 1990-1996 and undated (Box 2)
Related Mmaterial
For nonpublished records produced by SAPAC see separate record group, Sexual Assault Prevention and Awareness Center (University of Michigan) records.